<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et tw=80 formatoptions+=t : -->
<protocol name="input_simulation">

  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2017 Drew DeVault

    Permission to use, copy, modify, distribute, and sell this
    software and its documentation for any purpose is hereby granted
    without fee, provided that the above copyright notice appear in
    all copies and that both that copyright notice and this permission
    notice appear in supporting documentation, and that the name of
    the copyright holders not be used in advertising or publicity
    pertaining to distribution of the software without specific,
    written prior permission.  The copyright holders make no
    representations about the suitability of this software for any
    purpose.  It is provided "as is" without express or implied
    warranty.

    THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD TO THIS
    SOFTWARE, INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
    FITNESS, IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY
    SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
    WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN
    AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION,
    ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF
    THIS SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="input_simulation" version="1">
    <description summary="simulates global input events">
      This protocol allows clients to simulate input events, which the
      compositor will process normally. These events could be passed to other
      clients, trigger keybindings in the compositor, etc. Note that real input
      events will continue to be processed while simulators are in use.
    </description>

    <request name="get_keyboard_simulator">
      <descripton summary="create an input_simulator for a wl_keyboard">
        Creates an interface that can be used to simulate keyboard input events.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="keyboard_simulator"/>
      <arg name="keyboard" type="object" interface="wl_keyboard"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="keyboard_simulator" version="1">
    <description summary="layer metadata interface">
      An interface that may be implemented by a wl_keyboard, which allows
      clients to simulate input events from them.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor" />

    <request name="key">
      <description summary="simulates a key event">
        Raises a wl_keyboard.key event on the focused client(s), or processes
        the key for the compositor's internal use. The compositor will assign a
        serial and time appropriately when the event is emitted.
      </description>
      <arg name="key" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="state" type="uint"/>
    </request>

    <request name="modifiers">
      <description summary="simulates a modifiers event">
        Raises a wl_keyboard.modifiers event on the focused client(s), or
        processes the key for the compositor's internal use. The compositor will
        assign a serial appropriately when the event is emitted.
      </description>
      <arg name="mods_depressed" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="mods_latched" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="mods_locked" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="group" type="uint"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

</protocol>
