<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et tw=80 formatoptions+=t : -->
<protocol name="surface_layers">

  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2017 Drew DeVault

    Permission to use, copy, modify, distribute, and sell this
    software and its documentation for any purpose is hereby granted
    without fee, provided that the above copyright notice appear in
    all copies and that both that copyright notice and this permission
    notice appear in supporting documentation, and that the name of
    the copyright holders not be used in advertising or publicity
    pertaining to distribution of the software without specific,
    written prior permission.  The copyright holders make no
    representations about the suitability of this software for any
    purpose.  It is provided "as is" without express or implied
    warranty.

    THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD TO THIS
    SOFTWARE, INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
    FITNESS, IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY
    SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
    WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN
    AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION,
    ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF
    THIS SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="surface_layers" version="1">
    <description summary="create surfaces that are layers of the desktop">
      Clients can use this interface to assign the surface_layer role to a
      wl_surfaces. These surfaces are assigned a size by the compositor
      (generally understood to be the size of the output) and are rendered with
      a z-depth that corresponds to the layer they are among.
    </description>

    <enum name="surface_layer">
      <description summary="available layers for surfaces">
        These values indicate which layers a surface can be rendered in. They
        are ordered by z depth, bottom-most first. Typically shell surfaces will
        be rendered between the bottom and top layers. Multiple surfaces can
        share a single layer.
      </description>

      <entry name="background" value="0"/>
      <entry name="bottom" value="1"/>
      <entry name="top" value="2"/>
      <entry name="overlay" value="3"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="get_layer_surface">
      <descripton summary="create a layer_surface from a surface">
        Create a layer surface for an existing surface. This assigns the role of
        layer_surface, or raises a protocol error if another role is already
        assigned.

        Exclusivity allows you to instruct the compositor to avoid arranging
        other surfaces on top of this surface. For example, a compositor may
        avoid occluding your surface when the user maximizes a shell surface.
        However, compositors are permitted to ignore this flag under any
        circumstances they wish.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="layer_surface"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
      <arg name="output" type="object" interface="wl_output"/>
      <arg name="layer" type="uint" summary="surface_layer to add this surface to"/>
      <arg name="exclusive" type="uint" summary="1 to avoid occluding this surface, 0 otherwise"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="layer_surface" version="1">
    <description summary="layer metadata interface">
      An interface that may be implemented by a wl_surface, for surfaces that
      are designed to be rendered as a layer of a stacked desktop-like
      environment.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="remove xdg_surface interface">
        The layer_surface interface is removed from the wl_surface object and
        the surface loses the layer_surface role.
      </description>
    </request>

    <enum name="input_devices">
      <descripton summary="types of input devices">
        These flags are a bitfield and are used by set_interactive to specify
        what sorts of input the surface should interact with.
      </description>
      <arg name="none" value="0x0" />
      <arg name="pointer" value="0x1" />
      <arg name="keyboard" value="0x2" />
      <arg name="touch" value="0x4" />
    </enum>

    <request name="set_interactivity">
      <description summary="indicates that this surface is interactive">
        This request indicates to the compositor what kind of interactivity this
        surface requires. This may be chagned at runtime. Note that whether or
        not the compositor chooses to send the surface input events at any given
        time is implementation defined. Any events from input devices you do not
        ask for will be passed along to other clients, also in an implementation
        defined way.

        By convention, conventional compositors will send input events to
        surfaces below the shell surface layer when there are no shell surfaces
        or when the surface is clicked (and thus receives focus). Above the
        shell surface layer, the topmost surface receives all input of the types
        it requests.
      </description>
      <arg name="types" type="uint" summary="mask of input devices to use"/>
    </request>

    <request name="position">
      <description summary="configures the location of the surface">
        Sets the position of the surface in the layer in the wl_output's
        physical hardware coordinates (that is, within the range of 0 to the
        width of the wl_output given by wl_output.mode, inclusive). The size of
        the surface is taken from the size of the attached buffer.
      </description>
      <arg name="x" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="y" type="uint"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

</protocol>
