<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="wlr_exec_secure_unstable_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2018 Drew DeVault

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="a protocol for executing clients with higher permissions">
    This protocol allows unprivileged clients to ask the compositor to execute
    a program which can access protected Wayland protocols.

    The rationale for this protocol is that the execution environment of an
    arbitrary client cannot be reliably verified by the compositor. Environment
    variables like LD_PRELOAD may alter the runtime behavior of the client to
    malicious ends. However, if the compositor creates the client socket and
    exec's the client program itself, it can be sure of the client's execution
    environment.

    If a client is run with the WAYLAND_SOCKET environment variable set, it can
    assume that the socket represents an authenticated Wayland connection and
    it will be able to use any secure protocols it is afforded. If not, the
    client will likely connect to the Unix socket specified by WAYLAND_DISPLAY,
    but it will be an unauthenticated connection. If it needs authenticated
    protocols to accomplish its basic tasks, it will likely wish to use
    wlr_exec_secure_unstable_v1 to ask the compositor to execute itself again.
    It's at the client's discretion to exit once the compositor runs the second
    process or to wait for it to complete.
  </description>

  <interface name="zwlr_exec_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="interface for requesting execution handles">
      Clients which want the compositor to execute another client should create
      a zwlr_exec_handle_v1 and use it to configure and run the client.
    </description>

    <request name="exec_process">
      <description summary="creates a wlr_exec_handle_v1 resource">
        Creates an exec_handle for the requested command. The compositor can
        choose to disallow this request for certain commands, in which case a
        protocol error is issued. The command will be executed without a shell.
      </description>
      <arg name="handle" type="new_id" interface="zwlr_exec_handle_v1"/>
      <arg name="command" type="array" summary="the command to execute"/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        All objects created by the manager will still remain valid, until their
        appropriate destroy request has been called.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zwlr_exec_handle_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="an executing or to-be-executed process">
      This resource represents a process executed by the compositor, or a
      process which will be executed by the compositor shortly.

      The client should transfer any appropriate state, then send an exec
      request and await the exit event.

      Once the compositor receives an exec request, it should fork, close all
      file descriptors (except for the transferred ones), then dup2 them to the
      appropriate file descriptor number. It should then exec (with PATH lookup,
      e.g. via execlp or exevp) the requested command. Then it should send the
      pid event, followed by the exit event when the child terminates.
    </description>

    <request name="environment">
      <description summary="set an environment variable in the process">
        Sets an environment variable for the new process. The compositor can
        choose not to set any variables, including for example LD_PRELOAD.
      </description>
      <arg name="name" type="string" summary="environment variable name"/>
      <arg name="value" type="string" summary="environment variable value"/>
    </request>

    <request name="fd">
      <description summary="transfer a file descriptor to the process">
        Transfers a file descriptor to the new process. The compositor will use
        dup2 to assign the specified file descriptor number, then close the
        danging fd.
      </description>
      <arg name="fd" type="fd" summary="file descriptor to transfer"/>
      <arg name="num" type="uint" summary="first parameter to dup2"/>
    </request>

    <request name="exec">
      <description summary="start the new process">
        Asks the compositor to start the new process. Any request other than
        destroy after this point is a protocol violation.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="pid">
      <description summary="the process's pid is available">
        The compositor sends this after it has forked, to inform the client of
        the new process's pid.
      </description>
      <arg name="pid" type="uint"
           summary="pid_t of the child process"/>
    </event>

    <event name="exit">
      <description summary="the process has exited">
        The compositor will send this when the process has terminated, with the
        exit status. No further events will be sent after this, and further
        requests will be ignored.
      </description>
      <arg name="status" type="uint" summary="exit status of the process"/>
    </event>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="delete the exec_handle">
        Unreferences the exec_handle. If started, the associated process will
        not be killed. Sending any additional requests after destroy is a
        protocol error.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
